MICAH BOWLES

PHD RESEARCHER

EDUCATION

PhD Astronomy and Astrophysics, The University of Manchester 2020 - 2024

Computer vision, deep learning and imaging research for radio astronomy funded by the STFC and Alan Turing Institute (Python, PyTorch, bash, SLURM). See: list of publications.

- Lead research project managing two graduate summer students.
- Active collaborator in two data centric international research collaborations (Python, git, SLURM, bash).
- Founding member and chair of a machine learning partnership with the SKAO (industrial partnership).
- Founding member of a machine learning interest group in collaboration with Tsinghua University.
- Formulated clear ethics statement for both groups.
- Supervised by Prof. Anna Scaife.

MScR Astronomy and Astrophysics (Distinction), The University of Manchester

2019-2020

Researched explainable deep learning using self-attention (Python, PyTorch).

BSc Physics (2.1 Upper Second), University of Cologne

2012 - 2018

Completed a yearlong thesis research project on simulating merging galaxies (Python, Cython, FORTRAN exposure). See: [4].

WORK EXPERIENCE

NES Global Talent, Recruitment Consultant

02.2019 - 09.2019

Business development in a targeted approach to break into the renewable power financing sector (infrastructure investment). Coaching of team members on best data practices for their recruitment pipelines.

Omikron Systemhaus GmbH, Technical Translator

05.2015 - 10.2018

Translation of banking software, manuals, white papers, and marketing material from German to English, including the translation of a 500-page handbook for the newest software release. Omikron's offerings were translated into 10+ other languages using my English translations.

Deutsche Welle, Translator

10.2014 - 12.2014

Translation of a training handbook on international journalism from German to English.

Volunteering

10+ years of leadership roles within the Salvation Army in both Germany and the United Kingdom: participating in board meetings, budget meetings and running youth outreach programmes.

ACADEMIC PROFILE

Phenomenological & empirical computer vision and deep learning researcher interested in robustness, interpretability, and novel architectures (research published in NeurlPS, MNRAS, A&A). Participating in international collaborations, including efforts to build a terra byte scale radio astronomy data processing pipeline.

PERSONAL PROFILE

Passionate problem solver, gamer, and father. Most recently enjoying engaging in philosophy.

CONTACT

micah.bowles@postgrad.manchester.ac.uk +447555341585 Manchester, UK

GitHub

https://github.com/mb010 ORCID

https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5838-8405 LinkedIn

https://www.linkedin.com/in/micah-bowles-5863b0173/

SKILLS

Deep Learning
Image Classification
Explainable AI (XAI)
Data Visualisation
High Performance Computing
Agile Development
Leadership
Communication

LANGUAGES

English (Fluent) German (Fluent)

PUBLICATIONS

- [1] **Micah Bowles**, Matthew Bromley, Max Allen, Anna M M Scaife, E(2) Equivariant Self-Attention for Radio Astronomy, preprint arXiv http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.04742v1, NeurlPS 2021 Workshop.
- [2] Micah Bowles, Anna M M Scaife, Fiona Porter, Hongming Tang, David J Bastien, Attention-gating for improved radio galaxy classification, Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 501, Issue 3, March 2021, Pages 4579–4595, https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/staa3946
- [3] David J Bastien, Anna M M Scaife, Hongming Tang, **Micah Bowles**, Fiona Porter, Structured variational inference for simulating populations of radio galaxies, Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 503, Issue 3, May 2021, Pages 3351–3370, https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stab588
- [4] Persis Misquitta, Micah Bowles, Andreas Eckart, Madeleine Yttergren, Gerold Busch, Monica Valencia-S., Nastran Fazeli, 2020. Interactions among intermediate redshift galaxies-The case of SDSS J134420. 86+ 663717.8. Astronomy & Astrophysics, 639, p.A30. https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201937009

Conference Talks

[5] Paying Attention to Astronomy Data, NAM 2021 (long presentation).

Conference Posters

[6] Attention-Gating for Improved Radio Galaxy Classification, EAS 2021.